at what age do we learn how to have
better conversations
at what age should we learn to have
better conversations with ourselves
[Music]
knowledge is power
reality is
[Music]
what I would love to do so my podcast is
pretty free-flowing I have I literally
sometimes I have half page notes a whole
page today I have like one note I've
listened to you and there's a lot of
things floating around in my brain that
I want to talk to you about but um I
would love to if you don't mind start
with kind of your bio like who are you
what is it that you do how did you get
into this was it like profound all of a
sudden did you always think this way or
you know how do you get into all this
who are you that's a really good
question well thanks first of all it's
really a pleasure to talk with you and
gratitude and respect to your listeners
and so the name on my driver's license
reads Jennifer Ellis so Jennifer Ellis
is the name that my dad and my mom gave
me and I was born in Washington state I
grew up in Washington state and so I'm
inviting listeners to think about their
equivalent as I talk about this but one
of the things that I noticed that was
part of my earliest awareness was in
connection with the natural world I
always had a sense of peace and joy and
freedom and then also like a realization
that we're non-separate so my body was
part of the natural world the natural
world was part of my body and so I grew
up with just kind of like that Clarity
and that Joy of being aware of that
connection and so I'm inviting listeners
to notice for everyone who's listening
like what are your natural points of
connection because so one of the
foundations of our teaching I'm at a
wake yoga meditation and that's a
meditation Community geographically
we're in Baltimore and we have people
who join us online from all over
um but one of the foundations of our
teaching is that that's basic to All
Humans that we all have these entry
points into feeling connected feeling
whole feeling peaceful feeling really
inspired and excited and so for the
listeners the question is for me what
are those natural points of connection
and awareness
hmm well interesting so you grew up with
um you know basically what we would call
a non-dual awareness so so you know a
lot of people don't um it's very
difficult to understand these things
from a materialistic point of view um
for me I'd
I had some inklings of that growing up
but it wasn't until about five years ago
or so that I had um I kind of had like
some profound spiritual experiences and
I
um became vastly aware of the non-dual
nature of existence
um okay so so can you okay so I I just
asked somebody else this question the
other day to someone who uh for to a
completely materialistic mind who thinks
like you know this this is me that's all
that there is how would you explain
non-dualism
well so for me I thank you for saying
that like I've never actually put it in
those words but I think you're
absolutely right like that's a fair
description to me I would say I grew up
with natural Oneness and that natural
Oneness is natural like that's that's
like basic too to our human awareness
um so I think for someone who's had a
feeling of being confined within a
single human body that that's why I'm
offering that invitation is sort of like
form for each listener what are the
entry points like for example I've
talked to a rock climber who the day job
he's like a doctor and director of a
hospital medical director of a hospital
but when he's rock climbing the only
thing he's aware of is my right hand is
holding on to this rock and the next
move my right hand makes is going to be
to this rock and the same thing like
that total focused present moment
awareness so for that person rock
climbing is one of those moments of just
complete present full total awareness
for other people it could be music so
for people who love music sometimes
there's a kind of like I've heard
singers say this as well I gave a
compliment to a really talented singer
and the singer said I wasn't doing
anything at all and so there's a there's
thousands of hours of practice that go
into that singer being able to say I
wasn't doing anything at all but after
you have that thousands of hours of
practice as a singer as a musician then
the music just sort of pours through you
I think Yo-Yo Ma says it's like a whole
new universe can be be pouring through
you with every note and there's that
sort of like openness and when you
listen to Yo-Yo Ma you can feel there's
just like light pouring through that
music and so for every listener for some
people it's like they love animals or
they love nature they love being out in
the forest and so whatever it is there's
that connectedness with something that's
just really innocent and pure and
natural and it involves that that Focus
that being completely present
in a way that you're not even aware of
any limitation you're not aware of any
pain you're not aware of any like
stories there's no labels
so our conceptual awareness just kind of
like it's not present and there's just
complete focused awareness I think you
know sort of like kissing the top of a
newborn baby's head a lot of people have
that experience or like if you're
holding the hand of a dear one who's
about to depart the body like they're
about to leave the body or pass away it
can also be that same just complete
awareness that there is something so
much faster than can fit into a human
body
um well yeah like he said um uh you're
talking about how uh the the universe
you allowed the universe to pour through
you and it's not you acting as the
universe it's not the small self acting
through you know it's uh you you almost
must
um I'm a musician uh of sorts myself and
it's taken me a while to kind of learn
the essence of of not trying and not
sitting on a perch trying to catch
what's next but instead of getting out
of the way and allowing it to work
through me you know in in the the time
that you've spent working up to that the
10 000 hours as as this often said
um allows itself to kind of Express
through you and sometimes
um if you're familiar with uh Jazz so
like like jamming and jazz is very much
uh it's non-improvised it's very much
being present and just working with
what's there like you can't be in your
mind like oh I'm gonna do this like
you're not thinking about that you're
just here in your your talent expresses
itself and it creates something along
with these other band members so it's
really this dance um so what is it what
so what do you find in your teach
teachings like what seems to come up you
know when you're teaching someone this
from a place of
um you know maybe they have many more
years until they understand these things
um in non-j and not just an intellectual
way but in a experiential way
what are some things that seem to come
up like do they understand this at all
or is it what um so that's a really
really quickly
that there is
direct access that is available and I'm
not sure if that's because so our
meditation community so we are awake
yoga meditation and we're in Baltimore
we were founded by my teacher and his
name was Swami shankarananda and so
Swami Shankar Nanda I encourage you to
go to
awakeyogomeditation.org our webpage just
look at his picture and you can't do it
without just grinning because he's like
this being of light this amazing being
of light and so that energy of his
lifetime of practice like all of that
light that he generated in his lifetime
is here and so maybe that's one of the
the great gifts that we have in our
meditation Community is that people who
walk in the door feel that light and so
there's like a direct access that is
present and available that is a thing
that yogis say and I'm curious to ask
you about is it the same with musicians
but yogis say that it's really
indispensable to have contact with a
being of light like that and that that
gives you this huge spiritual boost
almost like this heart opening or this
calming of the mind so that the usual
chatter and usual patterns of thinking
just sort of melt away but I was curious
to ask you like if you've ever played
with a really established jazz musician
like when you were starting did that
help you enter into that free flow that
you were just talking about so
beautifully it's actually interesting I
never really um thought about that way
but I do have one of my dear friends
Eric nordina's name he's this fantastic
musician he's so good um and I got to
um
I've spent a lot of time with him but I
got to actually spend like a lot of
intimate time with him like we uh when
he first started we kind of like I
helped him kind of like write an album I
was I got to be around him as he was
just performing and existing and um
yeah yeah there is like a spiritual
Essence to that like there is a um you
know and now that I think about it I
suppose I've always gone to concerts and
I always really liked live music and
such and um you can instantly sense when
some something's not real like you can
tell the energy of the person on stage
is very um apparent you know
um so sometimes you just don't connect
with it like if they're incredibly
stressed out or they're you know miles
deep in thoughts I feel like you can
almost feel that in a sense but there is
also moments where
um
time itself begins it begins to cease
right because you're just this person is
creating this vibration you know with
their music with their words with their
presence and sometimes even just them
speaking on stage has brought me moments
of just you're just screaming yes inside
you know you you don't know you're not
thinking about anything you're just here
and it brings you to presence and that's
something that I've always just
um you know I think people who go to
concerts you know maybe great musicians
are their Guru in a sense you know
you're looking for that oh
you know because because just like that
picture you said that we're all we're
all when we find something somebody who
has it we're just we just want to follow
them right we're like you have it like I
don't know what it is but you have I
want to listen whatever you say I'm
listening you know so so it is that yeah
so so I have a I have had the grace to
be around
um musicians and not just Eric nordina
I've actually got to work with some
incredible people and watching them not
only right like pulling things from The
Ether
um and putting them into you know
pulling things from out here and getting
them onto paper and actually like
getting a recording of that it's like
whoa I just gotta witness that I just
gotta be around this person who is just
a conduit of the universe to get some
sort of like musical expression um onto
something that other people can hear
from from here forward so yeah yeah
certainly I think certainly yes
yeah it's such a gift I mean I would
just say it is such a gift because it's
so much larger than the individual and
so I'm really excited to hear you
describe that in musical form so that's
very much I think like what we are the
beneficiary of at awake yoga meditation
so that one of the words that Yogi
sometimes uses transmission that
transmission of spiritual energy is just
so whole and so vital and so filled with
peace and and just connectedness and
it's such a gift to have that oh yeah so
wonderful okay so so um what what sorts
of meditations do you guys teach over
there what type of meditation I mean I'm
sure a listener may have heard of uh
vipassana following the breath maybe
they've heard of um transcendental
Transit I always do this every time
trans Transcendental Meditation
um you know Mantra meditation these
sorts of things what is what is
something that you guys specialize over
there yeah absolutely so when you walk
in the door or when you hop onto one of
our meditations online so we have
meditations Sundays and those are in
person and then we also share them on
YouTube and zoom and then we also have
meditations Tuesdays and Fridays and
those are on YouTube and zoom and so
those meditations are very they give
like an opening invitation like if
people find it helpful to have a brief
focus and a brief guided meditation that
people can enact if they want and then
we have about 20 minutes of Stillness
and so in the 20 minutes of Stillness
you either can put into motion the
guided meditation that we just sort of
gave brief prompts for or you can
practice whatever your favorite method
of meditation is if you have a practice
already established we also my teacher
was a kriya yoga master so that is a
method of meditation that came from
India and so he was amazing as a Korea
yoga teacher and when he left the body
as Yogi say when he passed in 2014 he
appointed me his successor and asked
asked me to teach kriya yoga so that's
like a meditation that's taught
one-on-one and so it's individually
taught from the teacher to the student
and it involves about 20 minutes of
meditation in the morning and 20 minutes
in the evening so it's very integratable
into daily life it's also very potent
and transformable it's transforming so
it gives you like this technique of
self-transformation self-healing working
with what we've been talking about sort
of like helping you be extraordinarily
focused and present right where you are
helping you be more of you and then so
you were using that I think your
metaphor might have been like that like
that energy that frequency it helps you
be more of your own signature energy and
your own signature frequency so whatever
you are here to share it helps that come
into more direct View
um well okay so is this through um I
mean you said it's three you know 20
minutes of meditation and then a
conversation is are these like Koons
that you're kind of creeping them
towards are you unwinding things that
they are not um what is it what are
these conversations like so I mean so
basically if someone you can visit our
website and we have more information on
kriya um there's like a video where I'm
talking about Korea as well but if you
sort of like contact us you can email me
at Swami awake meditation.org and say
hey I'm interested in Korea and so that
would involve just setting up like an
hour-long conversation with me in which
I share
um a technique and then that technique
of meditation is you practice it in your
daily life 20 minutes in the morning 20
minutes at night and it's just helping
you be that which you are always and so
it works with breath and it works with
Mantra what you're really getting and
this is my experience from having
received these techniques from my
teacher who I mentioned is just a being
of light what you're really getting is
not only the technique it's also this
huge boost of spiritual energy as well
okay so when you first started learning
meditation I mean I know you said you
kind of had this uh recognition of
Oneness since you were since you were a
child um was meditation incredibly easy
for you at the beginning do you remember
any of your of your quarrels I'm always
trying to pull in um like people who are
just beginning or they don't know much
about this maybe this is the first
episode they stumbled upon and they
don't really know any of this like like
what what might they be coming across
and what did you come across
well so I mean the the answer is by
Grace yes um I mean I recognized
meditation as soon as I started
practicing it it was sort of like oh
this oh yes
so oh I'm so vibration um yes
um I also I mean I've I've been serving
as my teacher's successor since 2014 so
I'm happy to just offer some you know
commentary or observation about having
shared the technique with meditation
students and things that people notice
um so I think that the things that
people notice like one very frequent
refrain is I just feel so much more
peace I just feel so much more calm I
feel so much more focused I can close my
eyes anytime I need to and I can connect
with that you didn't use this word but
you were kind of describing it there's
like a current of inspiration that each
of us has the ability to connect with so
whatever our work is like we might be
writing computer code or we might be
like in a really high-powered corporate
job or we might be whatever we're doing
wherever we are
that energy it's just pure Creative
Energy so you were talking about sharing
it through music but it's like whatever
you're doing whoever you are wherever
you are it connects you with that
Pure Life Force and then it helps you in
your own body your own heart your own
mind bring joy and Harmony so that
you're able to choose how would I like
to respond in this particular moment and
so what happens is we become
increasingly aware of wherever
our pain points are or our reactivity is
we become aware of those and able to not
react and not enter into the sort of
like lower frequency the anger or the
fear or the frustration or the doubt or
the limitation wherever that we have
humanly felt blocked before that
increasingly dissolves and it melts away
and we're bringing healing we're
bringing compassion we're bringing
wisdom we're bringing awareness in
humanly felt I really like that that's
wonderful yeah yeah we're all just
humans right um uh okay so you I want to
transition over to your book um could
you tell us about your book so if I
let's do um you know if we just stepped
on an elevator together and and you had
to give me a pitch and there's a slow
elevator but uh uh and you're like oh
I'm an author I've written a book what
would it be about what is your book
about
okay well we can do a really fast
elevator first so so if you go to awake
yoga meditation.org you'll find there's
a book called awake The Yoga of pure
awareness and the fast elevator talk is
it's about how to live in joy and
freedom right where you are right in the
midst of daily life
and if you want a slightly longer
elevator talking yeah yeah it's it
shares yogic teachings so we are a
meditation community in the yogic
tradition it's also shares teachings
from the Buddha the one who is awake and
then it also shares teachings of
ordinary humans we're we're really
focused on sort of how do you do this in
your daily life what does this look like
like as a human with a human body on the
human emotions and human thoughts Human
Relationships human work in our time in
our space like how do you do this and
what does this look like um and so we
also just share like inspiring uh Vivid
relatable stories about humans who who
are living these teachings and living
these truths
um cool wonderful uh do you have off top
of your head I mean I'll definitely link
your book down below um I'll link the
website down below so everybody can
click on that and definitely check this
out um but do you have any of those
stories off the top of your head um like
any relatable human human level stories
well so one of the ones that left into
my mind as soon as you said that and
you'll you can read Fuller details in
awake The Yoga of pure awareness but one
of the stories is about a mom who made
the decision to donate her son's heart
her son was on life support
um and he was an organ donor and so she
sat next to his bedside before the life
support was removed and his organs were
donated and she listened to his heart
for an entire day and she just had her
ear up against his chest just listening
to his heart just memorizing his
heartbeat and it turns out that human
hearts are as unique as fingerprints
there is a signature heartbeat for every
human heart and it turns out that she
later met the person who had received
her son's heart and she said to him I
know this is going to sound really
strange but may I listen to your heart
and he said yes and she put her ear up
against his chest and she listened and
she was like that is my son's heart that
is my son's heart I would know that
heartbeat anywhere and so this is the
idea that the heart of each of us is
actually so much larger than this
physical body and and that was the way
in which she lived that realization so
we are each living that realization
always like the reality is when you're
aware of how interconnected we are we
affect hundreds of people some of whom
we know some of whom we don't know and
then that ripples out so thousands upon
thousands are affected so every time
we're choosing kindness every time we're
choosing Good Humor every time we're
sharing like you're talking about
musicians just sharing that Joy sharing
that incredible Creative Energy It Goes
Forth and the world changes the energy
of the collective the energy that's
available in the whole world changes so
the heart of each of us is actually
walking around
in everyone and her story just makes
that really Vivid
yeah well I I think of a few things um I
I do think about the the difference I
feel like I had some understandings of
uh or maybe understand this isn't the
correct word but of kind of the
difference between acting from the heart
and acting from the mind and that they
could they could hold hands beautifully
like they can they can work together but
um
I I do yeah it's almost like the heart
is our connector to the universe and and
we could all get caught up you know just
being in the mind and um you know and
just being a human to protect ourselves
we put armor around our heart right you
know we have these various
um you know ways of of
pain is pain is so painful sometimes
right and so our mind seems to kind of
jump in and we'll intellectualize well
I'm not gonna do that again and so we
put Gates around our heart and whatnot
um I
okay and one more thing that just it
came into my mind um I forget exactly
his name but he's his famous bodybuilder
uh Eric something perhaps but uh he
actually had to have uh he had his heart
replaced like he had to have a heart
surgery and he got someone else's heart
and um it's so interesting to hear him
talk about it because he started having
like afterwards the surgery went well
and he was healthy and everything
um uh he started to have like cravings
for certain things he started to think
in certain ways and uh he got to a point
where he's like I don't know how to tell
you this I don't know how to explain
this or verify this but I think my heart
was like a small Asian woman's heart and
she liked these sort of things and there
was basically like he had these
intuitions of of you know the heart had
a personality structure to it almost it
had um innate features and um I can't
recall exactly but I think he was able
to kind of confirm whose heart it was
and like match the picture to the yeah
that's that's who I think this Hearts is
you know so like how incredible is that
you know our heart has has a mind of its
own our heart has
it holds you know not only is the
connection to the universe like I said
but it's um yeah it holds a piece of us
doesn't it you know it's
it's quite incredible that is a gorgeous
description I am definitely immediately
going to Google that
oh yeah yeah I feel like his name's Eric
something I'll uh if I could find it
after this I'll send you I'll email you
a link but um he's very cool I've heard
him on a podcast talk about that
um so cool go ahead go ahead what you
were saying I mean as you were talking I
was just thinking what you were saying
is really apropos of a teaching that I
came across recently shared by Ramana
maharshi so he was an amazing Yogi from
India in the 20th century
um completely established in non-dual
awareness and he had a student whose
wife left the body whose wife passed and
what he said to a student who was
consumed by grief he said don't let the
Mind eat away at the heart
and so the heart is aware that we remain
connected beyond the physical and so he
was guiding his student to connect with
what is always present beyond the
physical and to not allow the mind to
eat away at that wholeness which is
always present and so then that becomes
the practice because of course like if
you are a human and you are facing loss
there's an adjustment and it's really
honest spiritually to say this is a big
adjustment that I'm going through and
humanly I'm experiencing grief right now
and it becomes much easier to move
through it gracefully to not push down
the feelings not deny them but also to
connect with that wholeness if we're
able to connect with that connectedness
which goes so far beyond the physical so
that we know like if someone leaves the
body our relationship with them does not
actually end we're still able to connect
with what in them is real and their
awareness their love their strength
their unconditional caring and support
is with us and then we're able to be be
a yogi the bugger is assessed to us
always I mean it says be a yogi no
matter what so we're able to be a yogi
and work with the mind like in a really
compassionate and wise and honest and
aware way
um
um and you I uh I I feel an opening to
talk a little bit about death I always I
do Wonder
um
I I'm very open and comfortable and have
understandings of of death these days
um but I do see where uh it instantly
closes off some conversations it
instantly makes people so
um I mean we want to run from it you
know just kind of like our Western way
of thinking of things
um I'm not sure how we got to got to
this point because it's of course the
it's the other side of the coin of life
right you know I don't think any of the
none of this would possibly be so
beautiful if we didn't um you know have
an ending of it but
um what have you learned about death or
what do you teach about death or or how
do you you know you know those of us is
of course it's difficult to
to try to face what we think about death
as a person you know right after someone
we love has just died you know it's very
difficult for us you know for someone to
go well that's just the way it is isn't
that beautiful you know of course you're
not going to see that you know
um they're they're hurting so
um I don't know do you have any do you
have any thoughts about about death
um and kind of like how our culture
you know maybe covers over it or you
know maybe how we could begin to see it
differently as a whole
one of the things so I'm happy to just
share a few observations one of the
things that Yogi say is as long as we're
identifying ourselves with the body then
we're identifying ourselves with what is
temporary and what is limited and they
also say fear will be present because
we'll be afraid of losing this body and
so they say then we're not living from
True awareness we're not living from
this recognition of that in us which is
beyond the body and so that is possible
to become aware while we are still in
the body of what is beyond the body and
then when you're in contact with what is
here that goes beyond the body then
there isn't fear present and there's
sort of an awareness of I mean I can
even use a little bit of humor but I for
example yesterday
um I was up at work I was wearing these
boots the socks that I was wearing were
slightly too big to go with those boots
so the boots were like too tight and I
was like well I'm gonna keep going in my
two type boots and it's gonna be fine
and it was fine but when I got back from
work I was like oh what a sweet thing to
step out of those two tight boots
and so actually from a yogic perspective
that is the way that the light in US
feels when we go beyond the body when we
leave the body from the perspective of
spirit it's amazing and I also want to
really immediately say stay here every
moment that you have to stay here in the
body stay here and be fully here
and when the time comes
do not fear
absolutely do not fear
yeah
I find that we often make up um you know
maybe makeup isn't isn't the right word
but we kind of have our residual stories
of of you know heaven and hell
um
I think um there's a way I see of people
coping with
um with death
uh and I'm trying to be careful because
I don't want to be insensitive or
disregarding what someone what someone's
beliefs are but um I I do find like okay
this person passed and so they're
they're now in heaven
and there's a way that that's totally
true you know they are they have
returned to the everything in a sense um
you know but but who they were when they
were here only really exists within you
you know
um and I don't know if we always have
access to that um
um I don't know do you have any thoughts
about I guess like uh you know heaven in
in the afterlife and and you know maybe
even reincarnation what is your what's
your experience and or thoughts on
reincarnation too
when I so when I first met my teacher
Swami shankarananda one of the things
that he said is I want what's beyond
heaven
so the the traditional yogic teaching
I'm happy to share that and then I'm
also happy to share my perspective on
the traditional yoga teaching the
traditional yogic teaching is that it's
possible to go beyond heaven so when we
are in contact with that in us which is
pure Consciousness pure awareness what
we've been talking about all along and
we're positing that's here like it's
already here that's natural it's who we
are eternally so when we're in contact
with that which we are eternally then
we're able to live in joy and freedom
while we are here in the physical we
will still have experiences in time and
space so we still experience the pairs
of opposites the yogis describe this as
Pleasure and Pain they describe it as
victory and defeat they describe it as
gain and loss and so the pairs of
opposites are still here when you're in
contact with the source of that
there's a lot less clinging and there's
a lot less fear and there can be in
enjoying of the Eternal of absolute
peace independent of what's happening in
time and space independent of what you
are experiencing in your body or your
heart or your mind and so that right
there that awareness the yogis actually
describe as being beyond heaven because
so what the yogis say is that
as we
lift our awareness as we shift our
vibration and we choose this energy of
Peace we choose this energy of kindness
we choose this energy of how much love
and wisdom and understanding am I
sharing with myself and also with all
then that is the energy that we generate
that is with us after we step out of the
physical and so it's what we will enjoy
we will experience that we will just be
even more of that energy of joy and
kindness and brightness and Freedom the
ability to create just by thought so you
know like in time and space you might
save up money for years to buy the
materials to build the whatever it is
but by thought it's possible beyond the
physical to create so there's that
amazing gift and then the yogis say that
there will be a time when we are again
inspired to learn what it is possible to
learn only in a human body and so there
are certain things that right now for
you you and for all of the listeners and
for me it's only possible to learn
through being in that particular human
body that you are in and so that's why
I'm saying don't rush it like don't be
in a hurry believe because your soul
wants to be here in that body I know
your human self might have other
opinions occasionally but from a sole
perspective whatever it is that you're
going through is absolutely perfect for
soul growth and for soil expansion and
so I mean to put like really specific
things on it like say that someone is in
a healthy able physical body for X years
like the first 30 years of being in the
body but then there might be a period of
great physical challenge for the next 40
years let's say from the Soul's
perspective that's not wrong like that's
not a mistake like from the Soul's
perspective the soul learns something it
could only learn in an Able Body for 30
years and now it's learning something it
can only learn and what we would call a
handicapped or disabled body or a body
facing extreme challenges for those 40
years and so it's really important to
not judge like to not think from a human
perspective well there's something wrong
with that person because they're
experiencing that also it's appropriate
to assist and to offer every
compassionate health and assistance and
support to everybody whether that body
is able or whether that body is what
humans call disabled but to sort of like
let go of judging it from a human
perspective because whatever the soul is
going through is amazing for soul growth
for this sort of like how much love how
much wisdom can I possibly generate in
this human timeline
from my perspective it's all now and so
it's only from the linear human concept
of time which has past present future in
a linear plane that it is reincarnation
from my perspective it's all now so from
the now all the timelines are
simultaneous and you actually can
experience it if you let yourself just
be fully present in the now
all the timelines are simultaneous and
one of the things that that means is
possible in the now to send healing out
through any timeline so it's possible in
the now to radiate healing to yourself
like say that a listener experienced
trauma at age 24 or age 14 or age four
from the now it is possible for that
listener to send healing to send
wholeness vitality and peace and their
24 year old self 14 year old self
four-year-old self will actually receive
that healing
because the the human timeline which
sort of sees it as being like if you've
ever seen those horses with uh they have
like the blinkers over their eyes so
they can't look that's like the human
timeline that sees past present and
future like in a single kind of line but
from the now all the timelines are
and so we're able to send this wholeness
this healing this health this Vitality
this peace this freedom to all the
timelines
wonderful perspective I thank you so
much for sharing that I really like the
way you put that it truly is you know it
reminds me of I'm sure you've heard of
like the Law of Attraction right
um the the Law of Attraction kind of uh
the over and over it takes so it takes a
while to really like try to
um I understand I suppose what they're
trying to say about their um it's not
about wanting that thing it's about
acting as if you already have it you
know it's it's about
um
embodying what it what it must be like
to experience that thing not come from a
way of wanting I'm Alan walk Alan Watts
the philosopher has uh the backwards law
you know if you're consistently trying
to get away from something you're trying
to act from a place of
Desiring that thing you are proving to
yourself that you don't already have it
you know in in a sense so yeah yeah I
love the man the time is always one of
one of my most fascinating subjects and
I love how um uh time time becomes so
one of the most fascinating things ever
in this spiritual world you know in any
of these studies of of uh spiritual
philosophy or spirituality like time
itself it's a lot of our um you know for
complete lack of a better word our
prison you know our this is a wonderful
beautiful prison that we have in this 3D
3D existence here but
um yeah like a lot of a lot of our
freedom is found through the perspective
of the Soul you know and in the soul
exists out of space and time um so so it
gives you a meta perspective of what
you're going through while you are in
space and time in a sense right
yeah
um I I did I I okay so I would like to
talk about yoga a little bit um
I think uh you've probably answered this
question in various ways um before on
podcasts and in conversations but um uh
how do we how do we unwind so so say
someone who's listening right now um
when I say yoga or Yogi they think of
you know either
um you know someone someone wearing
orange
um in Tibet or they think of yoga as
like a physical body movement like you
go to a yoga class and it's it's
stretching you know um uh how how would
you explain yoga to um you know maybe
bring someone to the to the definition
of of you know Union with God the the
Yoke of of all um how would you get
someone from the difference of I'm going
to a yoga class and it's it's breathing
and um hopefully I don't fart you know
and um uh to to Union with God what's
the what's the jump here that you would
perhaps explain
awesome question so I was just smiling
so I I do have myself a yoga Asana
practice and so respect and joy for
everyone else who loves yoga Asana and
that's often what's hot at a yoga studio
and I was laughing because for me one of
the things I always noticed was
sometimes people came to class with very
stinky feet so sometimes you're sort of
noticing the very pungent feet of
someone else who's in the class
um so but um besides that what the yogis
teach traditionally is that yoga Asana
prepares the body for meditation and so
that so after you've done your yoga
Asana practice then there's a kind of
calm and a kind of quiet the energy is
moving freely and so then you're ready
for meditation and so what we teach at
awake yoga meditation is Yoga philosophy
and sort of like those teachings of
universal Oneness and how to live in joy
and freedom in a human body in a human
heart in a human mind in a human life
and so it's I mean mean I would say in
some ways more accessible because you
know like no special postures are
required you can meditate sitting in a
straight back chair if you prefer if you
are a yogi who likes to sit in like
Lotus that's absolutely great to
meditate in that position as well but
it's not required so it's possible to
sit in a comfortable chair and then the
other thing that I would say is that the
yoga that we teach it's immediately
accessible so it's like right there in
the midst of doing your dishes or having
that conversation with your family or
being in your workplace that's where
your yoga is like it's it's everywhere
so it's how do I live from that kind of
awareness and that kind of kindness just
being more of my true self right in the
midst of my daily life
um yeah yeah it kind of reminds me of uh
when I learned to meditate like it took
me I feel like it took me a couple years
to uh in romdas puts it in a nice way
you know the goal is not to be a good
meditator it's to be free you know it is
so at the beginning I was always like I
got it I gotta do this at exactly this
time it's gonna be exactly this long and
and I'm I'm meditating my eyes are
closed and I'm breathing and I'm you
know like you just super exact about it
and then after a while this this
beautiful thing starts to happen in your
Waking Life
um where like you said you're doing
you're doing the dishes and you realize
you're just doing the dishes and you're
not having a conversation 10 layers deep
with your co-worker that just happened
earlier and
um you know you're present in this thing
I I also um when I first began I was so
obsessed with meditation when I I would
countless hours I just had this I
couldn't stop meditating and doing yoga
I was so obsessed with at the beginning
um I used to I would go to the airport
like kind of early so I could sit with
my eyes closed at the airport
um and just like so I can you know I met
like okay if people are looking at me
like cool sit with that what's that feel
like and then there was some training
ground for that but now it just feels
sort of silly now I can just be at the
airport doing whatever I'm doing but
also meditating right you know just just
being aware of where I am and uh you
know that that's that's my yoga too
right
um yes uh yeah yeah I love the the
transition the
the
letting go that that that yoga can bring
you know um the I I do think a lot of us
really do benefit greatly from you know
the actual physical practice of yoga
whether it's going to a class with other
people or me when I first began I did a
lot of YouTube
um I really
um I was very self-conscious person and
so I didn't want to like have people
look at me while I'm making weird faces
or anything like that like now I could
care less but I'm at the beginning
that's sort of what I needed so
um just like the the freeness the the
openness to kind of like
um just being that a lot of the breath
and the stretching we you know we hold
all this tension in our body right you
know so so being able to like loosen
that and let go of that through the
breathing and the stretching and in the
the physical movements and the um yeah
it really it really gives you gives you
a lot of a lot of presence so um do you
guys practice do you guys have a have a
practice at your at your Center do you
guys have a Daily Yoga practice physical
body yoga practice so what I'm what I
will do is I will share Asana and I will
share techniques for people to help them
ground The increased spiritual energy if
that makes sense so when people are
meditating some bodies have a process of
adjustment to having this more spiritual
energy and so it can be really helpful
so I will individually share practices
with people we don't at present have
like a Daily Yoga Asana practice it's
not part of our current offerings I
would be very open to it just because I
think as you said it can be incredibly
joyful and peaceful and freeing and it's
it's an absolute gift I agree with you
yeah yeah stinky feet and all
yeah I mean that really is another funny
thing of classes is I try to remind
people anytime I have anybody go to a
yoga class with me or something
um you know as easy as it is to to find
the thing that we complain about at the
end or find the you know the silly fart
or whatever part of the yoga is is not
just the physical right it's the
observing my mind oh the oh there's
judgment you know there's oh oh there's
Judgment of of that person or oh there's
Judgment of myself or
um uh oh there's uh regret that I ate
that that burrito three hours before you
know that's
um you know and they're just thoughts
and they're keeping you from being fully
here so
um yeah yeah that's wonderful um so okay
so did you I I briefly asked you about
it did you have
um
I'm very interested in in like these uh
I really am fascinated by like
near-death experiences and profound um
spiritual Awakenings like for people
that are completely non-spiritual and
then they have some sort of um you know
they're shot out of their body in some
sort of way and their their whole world
flips up to you know their whole
trajectory of who they thought they were
and whatnot is is just different from
this point forward
um Kundalini Awakenings that sort of
things
um did you have any experience of that
or or do you have any
um do you teach anybody with experiences
of that or any any perspectives on you
know profound sudden Awakenings well so
for me you might have kind of gathered
this as a result of that early awareness
for me there's just always been a kind
of natural Oneness that has been part of
my awareness and part of my experience
and so not a feeling of being limited to
a single individual human body and so
for me I met my teacher Swami
shankarananda in 2010 and that was a
major Catalyst like just a huge
unfurling of light and joy and peace and
recognition
um and it's it's very very natural so it
can just happen like in a very natural
Simple Pure like it just helps you be
more filled with peace it helps you be
more filled with joy and yes I mean it
is very true that people who come to the
meditation community and who practice
career you'll go yes absolutely like
they have Awakening experiences like you
have mentioned
um and then I imagine you guys help them
kind of stabilize
um you know because it is it is
certainly a jarring I mean I was in like
a I was in some sort of psychosis
luckily I was set up in um in an
environment where all I could think to
do was meditate and and do yoga and like
study all this stuff and just I was
reading all these books and and
listening to YouTube videos and luckily
I was in a position at that time in my
life where I could do that but man I
think of um sometimes I wonder about
like you know we have these things in
our culture you know psych wards and um
you know we call people schizophrenics
and and all these things and sometimes I
wonder if they if they had
the right teachings and the right
teacher could they understand and kind
of get that that energy
um more balanced and kind of maybe it'll
take a little bit a bit of work but kind
of become a more stable version of of
what has happened to them
it's a really good question I mean to
comment on what we help with in our
meditation Community yes like it's not
scary it's not traumatic it's a process
of becoming aware of wherever healing is
helpful in your own body in your own
heart and your own mind and so that has
like a different trajectory for each
meditator and it's very very natural and
it's a process that increases stability
um so there there's an increasing sort
of peace and balance and presence and
steadiness and Poise in the physical
structure but also like your emotions
and also your thinking as well so there
aren't as you were you were kind of
saying like it can be scary or it can be
you can feel like you've lost contact
with reality the way that medication
happens here at a weight yoga meditation
it's more like a gradual expansion of
awareness and there's just increasing
Clarity and peace and recognition of
wholeness this that has always been
present all along and I think it also
probably helps to have a community of
other people who are practicing as well
which sort of like
it kind of shows you everybody can do
this people from all backgrounds from
all walks of life all ages all body
shapes all body types like doesn't
matter what your nationality is or what
kind of accent you speak with like
everyone's welcome and and it is just an
increasing recognition of oh that's
what's been here all along
yeah beautiful
um okay we are getting up here in time
um I have two more questions so the
first one would be what is the the
future of your organization you know you
know looking forward in the next 20 30
40 50 years like where where you guys
headed um what would you like to see
happen
um uh where is the expansion you know
not even just from a business standpoint
but from a you know a spiritual
standpoint like like where what what
direction are you facing
who is my teacher I would encourage you
visit awake meditation.org just look at
his picture and it'll just make you grin
with joy
um just gave us the most incredible
Foundation he was a being of supreme
pure love and light just this sort of
like radiant effortless wisdom and light
and kindness and so that's our
foundation and what he taught was that
it's amazing just to keep your focus on
spiritual Purity so the yogis say
there's a process of purifying the heart
for each individual and that just lets
you know I think you were referring to
this earlier but just for each human
what are the the yogis describe it as
knots what are the knots that I can
untie and it happens naturally so I
would also just say like it's not
something that you have to figure out or
know in advance although you might
intuitively already know oh I would love
to heal that so but just as you meditate
naturally as you work with the
meditation those knots will melt and
they melt into light and what happens
then is you gain what I was talking
about the Soul's perspective on your
human Journey so you let go of judging
yourself and you let go of judging any
other human who has been part of any
experience that you've had there is an
acceptance and a gratitude and a respect
and then also an awareness that it's
possible to create what we love it's
possible to create in Joy it's possible
to create and freedom and so we just
have absolute Clarity and focus and
dedication about sharing that amazing
platform that amazing Foundation of pure
love and just sharing that energy of
wholeness and peace and vitality and joy
and there's a amazing energy that is
welcoming so anyone who walks in the
door like people have said I just burst
into tears because it just felt so
peaceful I mean people say for the first
time in my life I felt peace being here
and so it's just this this energy of
light and joy and excitement and
gratitude and gladness and so we love
sharing it um so anyone who's listening
who's sort of like yeah I'd like to
check that out um please join us we
meditate Sundays Tuesdays and Fridays
online anyone I'm in Baltimore
geographically the community is in
Baltimore geographically so anyone who's
in like Baltimore or DC Philly you're
welcome to come join us for an in-person
meditation there's nothing like it take
not Han said that meditating in
community is a miracle and so come find
out why like it's so much fun it's just
amazing yeah it amplifies the light it
just like amplifies the light and the
joy
um but also we share teachings on
YouTube on Facebook on Instagram on Tick
Tock as well so it's possible just
there's so many different entry points
we have e-courses online as well if
you'd like to check any of those out
oh wonderful okay cool yeah that's a
it's very training to me I do um I have
this uh this I do a lot of things on my
own like I could do it on my on my own
you know all these sort of things but I
of course know the importance of
community and um you know that's that's
some of my work is um um not trying to
do everything on my own um so it's
certainly something that's that Sparks
for me
um uh yeah yeah just um meditating with
a community that's something that I
would like to uh to lack of better term
challenge myself to try to do more often
so yeah I would encourage anybody
listening in that area to certainly go
go check that out in Baltimore
um how far are you from Philly
um I mean it's like two hours or
something like that on the train and
then I think I actually haven't driven
it in a while but we're we're in North
Baltimore which helps which helps with
reaching Philly yeah the treatment is
lovely though I'm sorry the train ride
is lovely I've taken the train I just
took like a week and a half ago I just
took the train from uh uh uh Middletown
to Philly uh and I've done that a couple
times it's just a lovely train ride it's
beautiful totally agree but also anyone
wherever you are geographically hop on
Zoom hop on YouTube and you can join us
the energy is also incredible online
it's amazing beautiful isn't that so
cool that we can you know it's it's been
so cool over the past few years with the
pandemic and whatnot to discover that uh
you could tap into this stuff online
like you wouldn't really think it's like
yeah it's different but maybe it is
different but it is it's there you can
you can really you can really feel it
actually even on Zoom classes and even
you know like this podcast I can really
connect with people on here and I there
was a while where I'm like I don't know
it screens and there's a you know I
don't know but it's it really is it's
been beautiful
very much
the work of light yeah uh yeah quite
literally a network of like uh through
the internet cables um okay we have we
have just a few more minutes um
I actually okay so you had something um
you were referring to someone who had
spent some time in prison
um on one of your videos on one of your
talks that you gave um and I watched the
clip of it and it was initially I had
watched it and I was like oh yes I want
to talk to her that sounds so awesome
she has this perspective
um but uh it was it start with started
with only the self suffers the self
um could you can you I know we're short
on time here but um could you could you
explain what you what you meant by that
or I don't know if it was your words
there or someone else's but what does
that mean only the self suffers the self
referring to what I think you're
referring to I came across an account
from someone who was in prison because
of his work on behalf of peace and on
behalf of justice and so what he said
was that during his time in prison
they were the happiest months of his
life because he got to meet himself
and he got to befriend himself he got to
be a companion to himself and everything
that came after that so after he left
prison he became a really important
figure
everything that came after that poured
forth from his knowing of himself and
then I think you might be referring to
there's a teaching from the
bhagavad-gita says that we are our own
best friend to ourselves and then the
reverse of that may also be true that we
may be the worst enemy of ourselves as
well and so what the yogis are saying is
that every time we choose to calm and
clear our mind and focus on peace focus
on what we would love to create Focus On
Healing focus on Building Bridges focus
on connecting focus on that network of
light what we're doing is making that
available not only for ourselves but
also everyone that we encounter even if
we never say a word
when we are in that energy you're on the
bus you're on the train you're driving
on the Beltway you're in the grocery
store you're in that board meeting that
energy of network of light and of peace
and a possibility and of wholeness and
of trust makes that available to
everyone and it changes what is present
in that organization in that family in
that relationship changes what is
present in your relationship to yourself
as well and so the yogis really do say
you don't have to go to prison to have
that experience but it's vital to let
yourself be a companion to yourself and
so for that human that was just his sort
of like he was in that crushing reality
like I don't want to minimize how
crushing that is to be confined and what
he found was that it turned into a
doorway to freedom and a doorway to
peace because he allowed all of the the
circumstances that he encountered
humanly to take him deeper into being a
companion to himself into realizing this
is true this is real this is what is
lasting this is what is vital this is
what matters when we establish our own
selves in what is true and real and
Lasting and vital in what matters then
silently that will permeate our families
our relationships our interaction with
our own body and our emotions and our
thoughts but also all of the
organizations if we're on boards or
we're in high paced fast-paced
high-powered corporate Realms those
organizations will transform
as we connect with this energy of
wholeness and health and vitality and
peace and it can happen silently it will
also of course shape the words that we
speak as well and so it will transmit
through those words but the yogis would
actually say that far more important
than those words that we speak is that
it's coming from that energy
so to allow yourself to be established
in that energy and then the words come
forth from that and the words actually
then this is back to where we started
it's spontaneous it's effortless it's
simple it's natural and it might be only
a few words it might be a smile it might
be a glance it might be just like the
way that you are in your body and the
energy of that meeting the energy of
that decision the energy that that sort
of is going forth and is being shared
through even very vast organizations can
be transformed
um yeah beautiful yeah it's like it
really can be without words it makes you
know the end of a yoga class A lot of
times we'll say namaste the light of me
sees the light in you and uh you know if
you allow that opening
uh how beautiful you know how beautiful
um okay one one bonus question this
could be just a quick one I always like
to ask this one what does the world need
more of right now
love just that energy of pure love that
energy of pure kindness spontaneous and
unconditional so sharing it naturally
using your skill set not looking for any
particular return from any particular
person not looking for any outcome but
just wherever you are being that pure
energy of kindness and it's also the
energy of inspired wisdom so that energy
of pure kindness will guide you
effortlessly to Insight and awareness
and inspired wisdom as well
beautiful beautiful I thank you so much
for your time I had I had a wonderful
conversation with you
um I I really appreciate your time I
really appreciate the work you guys are
doing I will most definitely in the
description below
um offer offer the links and links to
your book
um and yeah hopefully some some people
head that way and uh yeah this one this
was wonderful I really appreciate your
time thank you so much for this respect
to enjoy it's a pleasure talking with
you Jacob yeah yeah likewise Namaste
have a good rest of your day listeners
have a good rest of your day as well
love yourself drink some water and uh
see the light in one another
take care hello and welcome to the
junkyard love podcast
[Music]
learn to have better conversations with
ourselves
[Music]
knowledge is power
reality is
[Music]